Edward Roth medical school notes and medical practice case books
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Edward Roth medical school notes and medical practice case books
1878-1893
Ms Coll 47
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
10
(volumes)
Edward Roth was a graduate of Bellevue Hospital Medical College in New York city in 1880 after the required attendance of two years. The collection consists of ten volumes, the first five of which are Roth's notes on medical school lectures and clinics from 1878-1880. The remaining five include four volumes documenting his clinical practice in New Haven, 1891-1893, and one volume with a few entries on practice in Massachusetts in late 1893.
Roth, Edward, 1859-1919
Biographical / Historical
Edward Roth graduated from Bellevue Hospital Medical College in New York City in 1880. The curriculum at the time was two years in length. Shortly after graduation, about 1880-1882, he served as assistant to Dr. William D. Stewart at the Marine Hospital Service station in Vineyard Haven, Massachusetts. In 1883, he was practicing in San Francisco, where he married Eliza L. Beetle. From 1891 to1893, he was practicing in New Haven, and then went back to Massachusetts. He eventually returned to Martha's Vineyard where he practiced in Vineyard Haven for the remainder of his career. He died in Miami in 1919 on an annual visit to Florida with his wife.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes five notebooks of lecture and clinical notes from Bellevue Hospital Medical School, 1878-1880, covering anatomy, physiology, materia medica, obstetrics, diagnostics and therapeutics, diseases of women and children, nervous diseases, diseases of the genito-urinary system, and surgery. His clinical education notebook recorded the clinics he attended and the cases he observed at Bellevue Hospital and at Charity Hospital, Blackwell's Island. Four medical casebooks document his medical practice in New Haven from October 1891 to June 1893. They list over 1300 patient visits in the New Haven area, providing names, locations, and ailments. Indexes to each volume note the numbers of visits to each patient and fees charged. Although listed by the American Medical Association as an allopath, he may have been practicing an irregular form of medicine, as the ailments were general, his visits to patients were on a regular basis, and he recorded how many patients "renewed." A fifth case book contains a few pages of notes on patient visits made in Massachusetts in October, 1893.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 2014.
Medical education -- New York (State) -- New York; Medicine -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Roosevelt Island (New York, N.Y.); Lecture notes; Medical records; Medical students; Physicians; Bryant, Joseph D. (Joseph Decatur), 1845-1914; Flint, Austin, 1812-1886; Flint, Austin, 1836-1915; Janeway, Edward Gamaliel, 1841-1911; Keyes, E. L. (Edward Lawrence), 1843-1924; Lusk, William Thompson, 1838-1897; Robinson, Beverley, 1844-1924; Smith, Abram Alexander, 1847-1915; Van Buren, W. H. (William Holme), 1819-1883; Bellevue Hospital Medical College
- Series 1: Bellevue Hospital Medical College notes, 1878-1880
  - Volume 1: Lecture notes (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Notes written in ink on lined notebook with numbered pages. Notes on "Anatomy" taught by J. D. Bryant, pp. 1-72; "Physiology" taught by Austin Flint, Jr., pp. 100-186; "Obstetrics and Diseases of Women and Children," taught by William T. Lusk, M.D., pp. 200-259 (includes "Thomas Classification of Labor & its Causes," pp. 255-257, and also on two loose sheets); and "Practice" by Austin Flint, pp. 300-383.
  - Volume 2: Clinics, 1878-1879 (Box 2)
    This volume contains notes on clinics given at Bellvue Hospital Medical College, 1878-1879. Cases are numbered for each clinic and the diagnosis and treatment are recorded.
    Contents are: Medical Clinic by Prof. Polk at Bellevue Hospital Amphitheatre, pp. 1-4; Medical Clinic by Dr. A. A. Smith, pp. 5-7; Medical Clinic by Prof. Janeway, pp. 8-24; Medical Clinic by Prof. Flint, pp. 25-45; Medical Clinic for Throat Diseases by Dr. Bosworth, pp. 60-65; Surgical Clinic by Prof. Mason, pp. 67-69; Medical Clinic by Dr. Robinson, pp. 70-74; Diseases of the Heart by Dr. Beverly Robinson, pp. 75-77; Diseases of Women and Children by Prof. Lusk, pp. 85-88; Eye Clinic & Ear Clinic by Prof. Noyes, pp. 105-113; "Childs Clinic" by Prof. J. Lewis Smith, pp. 125-137; "Venereal Clinic" by Prof. Van Buren at "Charity Hospital, Blackwells Island," pp. 140-145; Surgical Clinic, by Prof. Keyes, p. 146; "Out Door Surgical Clinic, by Prof. Mott, pp 150-161; and Skin Diseases, "Clinical & Didactic," by Prof. Keyes, pp. 180-183.
  - Volume 3: Lectures on Practices, 1879-1880 (Box 3)
    Notes on lectures on "Practice of Medicine" by Austin Flint, pp. 11-154; "Diseases of Women" by William Lusk, pp. 165-219, and "Nervous Diseases" by Edward G. Janeway, pp. 225-265.
  - Volume 4: Lecture notes, 1879-1880 (Box 4)
    Lecture notes on Surgery, by William H. Van Buren, pp. 11-62; "Surgery-'Adjunct'," by Edward L. Keyes, pp. 65-70; Obsterics by William T. Lusk, pp. 75-172; Materia Medica and Therapeutics, by A. A. Smith, pp. 175-272 (continued in next volume). There is a loose handwritten leaf about Gay Head on Martha's Vineyard, Massachusetts.
  - Volume 5: Lecture notes, 1879-1880 (Box 5)
    Continuation of lecture notes on Therapeutics, 1880, pp. 11-40; and Physiology by Austin Flint, Jr., pp. 45-215.
- Series 2. Case Notes, New Haven, 1891-1893
  - Volume 6: Case Book, New Haven, 1891 October 19 - 1892 March 31 (Box 6)
    Roth wrote on the title page of this volume: "Dr. Roths Case Book "Y" New Haven Conn Oct 19th. 1891." There are two patient entries per page. The arrangement is chronological. Patients are listed with their address in New Haven or the name of a surrounding town or neighborhood (for example, West Haven, Waterbury, Stony Creek [Branford]). The patient's condition is described in broad terms such as headache, buzzing in ears, pain in chest, cough, discharge from nose, rheumatism, arthritis, thick phlegm, etc. If the entries contain treatments, they are in a shorthand. There is an index of patient names in the back, and notes about the number of "renewals." Another index lists money owed, but again there are abbreviations.
  - Volume 7: Case Book, New Haven, 1892 April 1 -1892 September 8 (Box 7)
  - Volume 8: Case Book, New Haven, 1892 September 8 - 1893 April 28 (Box 8)
    Contents similar to the above. There is a loose receipt for maintaining a postal box.
  - Volume 9: Case Book, New Haven, 1892 November 11 - 1893 June 15 (Box 9)
    Dates overlap with previous volume but cases are different.
  - Volume 10: Case Book, Springfield, 1893-1893 (Box 10)
    There are only five pages of entries for locations in Masachusetts dated from October 7 to October 24. One entry reads "Tinnitus Aurium 8 yrs. standing/ offered cure for $10."